# Yaw Wiafe-Akenten

Detroit, Michigan | wiafeakenten.yaw@gmail.com | +1 (716) 539-9267

# **SUMMARY**

Motivated, personable, and established professional with a successful track record working in the technology industry for 5+ years to include web development and design, coding, and programming. Experienced in Microsoft Office Suite, WordPress (HTML, CSS, JS), MATLAB, Adobe Creative Suite, Android Studio (Java), Unity (C#), and Unreal Engine (C++). Well-versed in the functions of production and videography including video and audio editing and graphic design. Reliable, flexible, and able to effectively adapt to and diffuse challenging situations. Well-developed skills in prioritizing, decision making, time management, public speaking, and verbal and written communication, to include fluency in German. Diplomatic and tactful with professionals at all levels. Accustomed to handling sensitive and confidential information. Proven ability to produce results and meet organizational goals under strict guidelines and build and lead successful teams. Strong ability to utilize and navigate multiple systems simultaneously and work collaboratively with a team and independently.

# **SKILLS/COMPETENCIES**

Application Programming Software Analysis & Design Database Design & Development
Product & Project Management Application & Unit Testing Process Improvement & Quality Control
Data Management & Analysis Scrum & Agile Methodologies Contract Negotiation & Cost Control

## **EDUCATION**

Wayne State University

Bachelor of Science in Chemical Engineering

Detroit, MI

August 2016 – Present

#### **WORK EXPERIENCE**

# Independent Contractor | Detroit, MI

June 2015 – Present

- Creates multifaceted high-speed websites, apps and platforms for companies throughout Michigan with a focus on products to include gaming, energy efficiency, organic skin care, environmental friendly manufacturing and education
- Responsible for recruitment and staffing of 66 part-time positions for start ups, small business, and non-profits specializing in event planning, business management, energy efficiency and marketing
- Coordinates and executes high capacity corporate and community events with budgets of \$100,000+ by developing
  event schedules and staff assignments, delegating activities and tasks, creating invite lists, distributing invitations and
  maintaining a database of volunteers, events and donors
- Managed over 50 individuals and provided administrative support for large scale events such as Arts, Beats, and Eats,
   River Days and Winter Blast
- Builds corporate and social client base by maintaining professional relationships with stakeholders, developing and negotiating contract agreements with vendors and exhibitors, and maintaining a social media platform

#### STEM Education Innovator | Michigan State University Extension, Detroit, MI

February 2019 – October 2020

• Develops programming, strategies, curriculums, and software (videogames, websites) to be used in the STEM education initiatives for MSU Extension and Wayne County 4-H

## Project Consultant | Jack Morton, Detroit, MI

July 2019 – December 2019

 Provides knowledge and expertise to develop strategies, events, and campaigns for companies (Chevrolet, Miller Coors) that involve technology and/or education

# Lead Instructor | Wayne State University, Detroit, MI

June 2018 – July 2018

- Developed and taught a weekly summer camp program to 40 children ages 12 -17 to create apps and develop websites and video games
- Created curriculum and materials to motivate children to learn, actively engage, and encourage feedback about topics such as computer knowledge, game design, programming and creating websites
- Encouraged student engagement through interactional learning by accompanying students on field trips to science and technological museums
- Incorporated learning styles such as directing and discussing to create and foster a positive and safe learning environment, maintain interest in topics, and encourage hands-on learning

#### Product Innovation Manager | Bamboo Detroit, Detroit, MI

September 2016 - April 2018

- Responsible for increasing company revenue by 32% through development of new products and systems such as company website, 2 internal apps and a virtual mail forwarding system
- Increased data gathered by customers and visitors by 200% through implementation of an electronic sign-in application and digitizing and streamlining customer inquiry, support and event services
- Maintained a relationship with 400+ customers and partners to develop and execute business and operational processes, initiatives, software, and technology, plan high capacity company events, and allocate rental space
- Improved business practices by digitizing data storage to enhance security of documentation for staff and customers and streamlined prices for event rental space for members and non-members
- Assisted with the hiring process by training and on-boarding new staff, developing marketing strategies for recruitment and managing interns and contractors

# Web Development Intern | SAGA MKTG, Detroit, MI

February 2017 – October 2017

- Carried out company requests by creating and designing wireframes tailored to the style and content of the company, integrating data from back-end databases, and maintaining, expanding and scaling the website
- Responsible for creating, building and maintaining 10 websites for Fortune 500 companies through the use of HTML,
   CSS, JavaScript and WordPress
- Participated in branding and marketing through the use of social media platforms such as Twitter, Instagram and Facebook
- Resolved software issues through performing system upgrades, patch installation, page testing, and collaboration with end users to address web requests and help desk tickets

#### **PROJECTS**

# Founder | Engineering Detroit / StemList.org

April 2016 - Present

- Responsible for teaching 200+ students curriculum such as engineering and computer science, coding, graphic design, and web development through educational programs with schools, universities and non-profit organizations
- Develops proposals, lesson plans, codes of conduct, and teaching manuals to execute curriculum and prepare students for college education
- Maintains relationships and networks with community partners and local schools to provide ongoing education and facilitate workshops to middle school and high school students

# Co-Organizer | HACKWSU 2017 / Code Detroit 2018 / DHACK 2018 / WSU Nexus 2020

February 2017 – Present

- Secured sponsorship from local companies to teach 3,000+ youth across the city of Detroit curriculum such as coding and entrepreneurship at community events
- Led operations for student outreach to high schools and colleges to include advertisement, recruitment, marketing and maintaining relationships with community stakeholders and partners
- Oversaw day-to-day operations for the events including curriculum and activities, negotiating and partnering with vendors, coordinating schedules, maintaining budgets, and recruitment of volunteers
- Facilitated meetings regarding event details such as vendor location, décor, catering, equipment, and guests

## **AWARDS**

# 2<sup>nd</sup> Place Winner | Startup Drive Detroit 2017

Feb 5, 2017

- Lead designer and developer in coding the app (Android studio)
- Lead team with making wireframes and making the wireframes a reality
- Assist team with business plan and market research
- Work with product owner to groom backlogs and deliver features along with leading scrum sprints

## Best Hack that Helps Someone / Best Use of SendGrid API | Spartahack 2017

Jan 22, 2017

- Assist team in programming hardware (Raspberry Pi and Intel Edison)
- Develop and execute designs of the technology
- Educate and implement agile methods, protect team from outside distractions, along with maintaining focus on project timeline and scope